<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-28T02:04:09-08:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Trey Fortmuller</title><subtitle>Jekyll version of the Massively theme by HTML5UP</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Waterproof Quadcopter Build</title><link href="/blog/waterproof/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waterproof Quadcopter Build" /><published>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/blog/waterproof</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/waterproof/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking “Intro to Control for UAVs” (ME136) in the Fall of 2017, the professor Mark Mueller recruited my lab team to design and build a quadcopter to be used in his lab for research purposes. One of his graduate students is working on launching a drone from the ocean. This platform will be a test rig to be used within the lab as the grad student works on modeling the dynamics of an aquatic launch and developing control systems to achieve this reliably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build had to employ the same flight controller that the lab already used for their various other drone related projects, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bitcraze.io/crazyflie-2/&quot;&gt;Crazyflie&lt;/a&gt; from Bitcraze, a PCB designed to drive brushed motors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Run the Crazyflie flight control board (an STM F4 microcontroller)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Have enough room for a radio based &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bitcraze.io/loco-pos-system/&quot;&gt;localization unit&lt;/a&gt; to use for state estimation&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Not too high of a voltage (limit to a 2S LiPo's 8.4V)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Compact, less than 200mm motor shaft to motor shaft&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Agile, at least a 2:1 thust to weight ratio&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Operate down to 3m of depth&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Full battery voltage telemetry&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;component-specification&quot;&gt;Component Specification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/waterproof/waterproof6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems engineering for a multirotor is a large optimization problem including factors such as motor stator size, motor KV, prop diameter and airfoil, battery voltage and capacity, and aircraft size, weight, and configuration. Thankfully the requirements for the platform narrowed down our choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We estimated we could meet all the requirements with a craft weighing around 100g. Based on existing motor thrust testing, we found that an 1104 7500KV motor could achieve 100g thrust on 2S running a 2inch prop, so we’d get a power to weight ratio of roughly 4:1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this, we decided on a 2S LiPo at 400mAh. Knowing that all our components would have to be submersible, we decided to look around 10A rated 4-in-1 ESCs (4 ESCs for brushless motors on one PCB for easy mounting inside a waterproof enclosure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our powertrain specified, we found the proper components on Amazon and began recreating them in CAD so I could design our frame and waterproof enclosure around them. The Bill of Materials for off the shelf components we included in the build is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Bill of Materials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-wrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;table&gt;
		&lt;thead&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;th&gt;Total Weight Contribution (grams)&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;/thead&gt;
		&lt;tbody&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.bitcraze.io/collections/kits/products/crazyflie-2-0&quot;&gt;Crazyflie Flight Controller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;STM F4 based microcontroller with an IMU and several UARTs&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.bitcraze.io/collections/positioning/products/loco-positioning-deck&quot;&gt;Bitcraze Loco Positioning Deck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;RF based locolization module&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/iPower-Motor-Brushless-Quadcopter-Torrent/dp/B01N7QDZY6/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510622724&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=1104+7500kv&quot;&gt;iPower iX1104 7500KV Brushless Motor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;Brushless motors&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/BLHeli_S-Electronic-Controller-Multirotor-Crazepony/dp/B076BDHCHX/ref=sr_1_4?rps=1&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510621639&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=20x20+10A+ESC&amp;amp;refinements=p_85%3A2470955011&quot;&gt;Wave 4-in-1 10A ESC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;Single PCB with 4 ESCs for brushless motors rated for 10A continuous&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Crazepony-400mAh-Battery-Racing-Quadcopter/dp/B072BH1XP6/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510622347&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=2S+400+mah&amp;amp;dpID=410fHvjWLiL&amp;amp;preST=_SY300_QL70_&amp;amp;dpSrc=srch&quot;&gt;Crazepony 400mAh 2S 7.4V 30C LiPo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;A small 2-cell LiPo&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Propellers-Compatible-6200-10000KV-Brushless-Transparent/dp/B074NP3LFF/ref=sr_1_1?s=toys-and-games&amp;amp;rps=1&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510622468&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=2inch+props&amp;amp;refinements=p_85%3A2470955011&quot;&gt;Gemfan 2040 Triblade Props&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;Some 2 inch diameter triblade propellors&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
			&lt;tr&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Matek-Systems-Adjustable-Switchboard-Continuous/dp/B01EACBW6E/ref=sr_1_fkmr1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511574313&amp;amp;sr=8-4-fkmr1&amp;amp;keywords=matek+5V+regulator&quot;&gt;Matek Systems Micro BEC 5V/12V Adjustable Buck Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;Battery eliminator, a 5V bucking regulator&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;/tbody&gt;
	&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/waterproof/waterproof4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main design constraint was the requirement that the vehicle must be submersible. Brushless motors are “waterproof” out of the box due to the insulating enamel applied to the wires of the motor winding in the stator, so those can operate underwater without issue. Everything else (flight controller, ESCs, localization module, voltage regulator, battery) would have to somehow be waterproofed or inside a watertight container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David, Joey, and I ideated on how we might protect the sensitive PCBs from the elements with a container of sorts. For the sake of preserving an ideal center of mass, close to the geometric center of the vehicle, we decided on two cases which sandwhich the frame of the quadcopter. The top case contains all the sensitive PCBs and the battery is protected by the bottom case. A hole is cut in the frame for the battery lead to reach the ESCs and regulator in the top case. 20+ hours of CADing in Fusion 360 later, I completed the full vehicle assembly including a custom frame, top and bottom cases, as well as gaskets to seal the cases against the frame. I included every single PCB as each would be mounted in the case and designed the cases around the components. This ensured a reasonable fit as well as the accuracy of the inertia tensor of the vehicle, an input to the PX4 firmware the lab had running onbaord the Crazyflies for flight control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/waterproof/waterproof_main2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electronics are mounted inside the top case using TPE mounting solutions, CA glue, heavy duty double sided foam tape, and M2 fasteners. There are 4 holes in the top case which allow the motor wires to reach the ESC board inside the case. Those holes would be filled with a rubbery silicon caulking with the wires threaded through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fabrication&quot;&gt;Fabrication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;watertight-cases&quot;&gt;Watertight Cases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/waterproof/waterproof1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D printing was the natural choice for frabrication of the custom cases, but normal FDM prints are not watertight. Small gaps between layers can allow some water to permeate even a thick shell of typical 3D printing plastics. SLA type prints (laser/projection based resin curing processes) are bound at a molecular level, so those are watertight. Thankfully at Jacobs Hall on campus at UC Berkeley, we had access to a Carbon3D printer for us to fabricate the cases. I had never printed anything with an SLA printer before, it was definitely a learning curve. This printing process has its own intricacies, there are different issues to debug than I was used to. It took 3 or 4 iterations before I figured out how to avoid vacuum pockets forming in the print, and how to arrange the support structure to avoid warping. Once I was happy with the part and its fabrication, I printed a top and bottom case in black “rigid polyurethane” on the Carbon 3D. All the Carbon3D resin chemistries are proprietary so beyond “polyurethane,” I really have no idea what the parts are made of, they were super durable though and I was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tpe-gaskets&quot;&gt;TPE Gaskets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weakness of our double case sandwich approach is the potential leak at the interface between the cases and the frame. We had seen rubber gaskets used in other systems at an interface which needed to be watertight. A flexible 3D printing filament called thermal polyurethane (TPE) came to mind. I designed some gaskets which fit along the footprint of the top and bottom case along the frame. They are meant to be compressed when the top and bottom plate sandwich the frame using a few M2 nuts and bolts. I printed the gaskets in orange &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/NinjaFlex-TPU-3D-Printing-Filament/dp/B01LXZYJ3R/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1514450027&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=ninjaflex&quot;&gt;NinjaFlex&lt;/a&gt; TPE on my personal Printrbot Simple and over-extruded the prints pretty severely to ensure better-than-average layer adhesion. The gaskets would be adhered to the cases with CA glue with the exposed interface between the case and gasket covered in watertight &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/MG-Chemicals-Silicone-Modified-Conformal/dp/B008O9YIV6/ref=sr_1_1?s=industrial&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1514450052&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=silicon+conformal+coating&quot;&gt;silicon conformal coating.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frame&quot;&gt;Frame&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, the custom frame would be cut from a 3mm thick plate of carbon fiber. It would be rigid, light weight, and durable. We had the carbon purchased, but unfortunately we were finishing this project towards the end of the semester. During the last week of class, the waterjet we needed to access in order to safety CNC cut the carbon was all booked up due to other class projects being due for many other students. Cutting the carbon on a typical CNC mill would be a hard sell to the machineshop technicians as carbon fiber dust is one of the last things you’d like in your lungs. 3D printing to the rescue again… we recruited our good friend Eric to complete a speciality print for us. Eric owns a printer with a number of upgrades allowing him to print abrasive and high temperature filaments. He printed us a frame out of 3mm of carbon-reinforced nylon, and extremely durable material. It’s not as clean as the carbon fiber plate we planned on, but it’s rigid enough to be flight worthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;assembly-and-delivery&quot;&gt;Assembly and Delivery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After removing excess pins, direct soldering all the components together, and installing a voltage divider for stepping down the input to the VBAT sensor, we covered all the electronics in 2 coats of silicon conformal coating for safety in the off chance that any moisture got inside the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/waterproof/waterproof3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modification to the PX4 firmware running on the Crazyflie is necessary in order for the PWM signal output to the ESC to be read correctly, and thus appropriately control the motors. PWM signal timing was adjusted to the standard 1000-2000 microsecond period, but the logic level of the signal worked out of the box. We also changed a hardcoded scaling factor to read the correct battery voltage from our new VBAT sensing resisor values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was certainly a design challenge and introduced me to an entirely different addative manufacturing process in SLA 3D printing. The more materials, processes, and printers I interact with, the more I see 3D printing as a promising engineering medium for research, prototyping, and manufacturing in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">A waterproof quadcopter built around the crazyflie flight controller for a professor researching aquatic drone launches.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/waterproof/waterproof_main.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Crazyflie Quadcopter Flight Controls</title><link href="/blog/cf-flight-controls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crazyflie Quadcopter Flight Controls" /><published>2017-12-06T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/blog/cf-flight-controls</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/cf-flight-controls/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;auto-generating-sitemap&quot;&gt;Auto-Generating Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sitemap is auto generated! Just simply change the front matter of each site. It looks like so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sitemap:
    priority: 0.7
    lastmod: 2017-11-02
    changefreq: weekly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspring-integration&quot;&gt;Formspring integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">A cascased controller implementation for autonomous loitering with Crazyflie quadcopter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Photogrammetry 3D Scanner</title><link href="/blog/3d-scanner/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photogrammetry 3D Scanner" /><published>2017-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/blog/3d-scanner</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/3d-scanner/">&lt;p&gt;I built this project with my friends Suneel and Nathan for UC Berkeley’s hackathon: &lt;a href=&quot;https://calhacks.io/&quot;&gt;Cal Hacks&lt;/a&gt;, one of the largest hackathons in the world. The event featured 1,700 hackers from 100 schools and 5 countries building projects for 36 striaght hours. It was an increidble experience, and a very professionally run event. After we submitted and presented our work, in a Redbull driven haze, we found out that we were one of six teams to win the Cal Hacks fellowship award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cal-hacks-fellowship&quot;&gt;The Cal Hacks Fellowship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  	Why do you have to stop when the hackathon is over? We’re introducing the Cal Hacks Fellowship, a program that accepts 5 hackathon teams to continue their projects beyond the hackathon. We plan to continue improving your project and move it past its initial stage so you can continue adding onto it, while receiving the same support from a hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
	This includes: One-on-one director mentorship, Work with industry professionals and venture capitalists, Receive support from The House Founders program, Gain access to future hack nights and unlimited amount of free resources. - calhacks.io
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were given $1000 to continue building our project out as far as we’d like. Suneel, Nathan, and I have plenty of ideas as to how to best use this money to turn our weekend project into a useful tool. Our original Cal Hacks submission for the project can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://devpost.com/software/greg-wt609e&quot;&gt;DevPost&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inpsiration&quot;&gt;Inpsiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D Printing offers quick and easy access to a physical design from a digitized mesh file. Transferring a physical model back into a digitized mesh is much less accessible in a desktop platform. We sought to create our own desktop 3D scanner that could generate high fidelity, colored and textured meshes for 3D printing or including models in computer graphics. The build is named after our good friend Greg who let us borrow his stereocamera for the weekend, enabling this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-build&quot;&gt;The Build&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3d-scanner/greg10.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rig uses a ZED stereocamera driven by a ROS wrapper to take stereo images at various known poses in a spiral which is executed with precision by two stepper motors driving a leadscrew elevator and a turn table for the model to be scanned. We designed the entire build in a high detail CAD using Autodesk Fusion 360, 3D printed L-brackets and mounting hardware to secure the stepper motors to the T-slot aluminum frame we cut at the metal shop at Jacobs Hall. There are also 1/8th wood pieces that were laser cut at Jacobs, including the turn table itself. We designed the power system around an Arduino microcontroller and and an Adafruit motor shield to drive the steppers. The Arduino and the ZED camera are controlled by python over a serial port and a ROS wrapper respectively to automate the process of capturing the images used as an input to OpenMVG/MVS to compute dense point clouds and eventually refined meshes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3d-scanner/greg_cad.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3d-scanner/greg11.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran into a few minor mechanical design issues that were unforeseen in the CAD, luckily we had access to a 3D printer throughout the entire weekend and were able to iterate quickly on the tolerancing of some problematic parts. Issues with the AccelStepper library for Arduino used to simultaneously control the velocity and acceleration of 2 stepper motors slowed us down early Sunday evening and we had to extensively read the online documentation to accomplish the control tasks we needed to. Lastly, the complex 3D geometry of our rig (specifically rotation and transformation matrices of the cameras in our defined world coordinate frame) slowed us down and we believe is still problematic as the hackathon comes to a close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-improvements&quot;&gt;Future Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re proud of the mechanical design and fabrication, actuator precision, and data collection automation we achieved in just 36 hours. The outputted point clouds and meshes are still be improved. This is a result of the ZED stereocamera we used, it wasn’t the right camera for the job as it is optimized for depth sensing up to 20m away, not 20cm away as in our build. It did however have an awesome advantages in that we could control it through ROS, so automating the activation of the camera through a python script was easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3d-scanner/greg_build.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the money we won at the hackathon, we are planning on purchasing an Nvidia TX2, to integrate all the automation and mesh contrusction onto an embedded platform that can be carried with the scanner. Also, we’ll purchase an XBox Kinect camera and try to rebuild around using IR depth sensing rather than photogrammetry. This method has been proven specifically for this close range application and we’re hoping to generate our first usable mesh during the Spring 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3d-scanner/greg4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-with&quot;&gt;Built With&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;6u 12u$(small)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;OpenMVG&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Arduino&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;ZED from Stereolabs&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;ROS&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;CUDA&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">A vision based 3D scanner utilizing photogrammetry to generate meshes, affectionately called 'Greg.'</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/3d-scanner/greg9.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Custom Electric Longboard</title><link href="/blog/e-board/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Custom Electric Longboard" /><published>2017-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/blog/e-board</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/e-board/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;auto-generating-sitemap&quot;&gt;Auto-Generating Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sitemap is auto generated! Just simply change the front matter of each site. It looks like so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sitemap:
    priority: 0.7
    lastmod: 2017-11-02
    changefreq: weekly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspring-integration&quot;&gt;Formspring integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">An electric longboard with a handheld wireless controller.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Midair Hotswap</title><link href="/blog/hotswap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Midair Hotswap" /><published>2017-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/blog/hotswap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/hotswap/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;auto-generating-sitemap&quot;&gt;Auto-Generating Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sitemap is auto generated! Just simply change the front matter of each site. It looks like so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sitemap:
    priority: 0.7
    lastmod: 2017-11-02
    changefreq: weekly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspring-integration&quot;&gt;Formspring integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">A mechatronics platform designed to autonomously swap a quadcopter's battery, without touching the ground.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Custom RC Transmitter</title><link href="/blog/custom-drone-transmitter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Custom RC Transmitter" /><published>2016-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/blog/custom-drone-transmitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/custom-drone-transmitter/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;auto-generating-sitemap&quot;&gt;Auto-Generating Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sitemap is auto generated! Just simply change the front matter of each site. It looks like so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sitemap:
    priority: 0.7
    lastmod: 2017-11-02
    changefreq: weekly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspring-integration&quot;&gt;Formspring integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Part of my final project for Design Innovation 22, an Arduino driven RC Transmitter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Robot Learning Lab</title><link href="/blog/rll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robot Learning Lab" /><published>2016-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/blog/rll</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/rll/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;auto-generating-sitemap&quot;&gt;Auto-Generating Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sitemap is auto generated! Just simply change the front matter of each site. It looks like so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sitemap:
    priority: 0.7
    lastmod: 2017-11-02
    changefreq: weekly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspring-integration&quot;&gt;Formspring integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Part of my responsibilities as an undergraduate research assisstant in Pieter Abbeel's RLL at UC Berkeley.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FPV Racing Quadcopters</title><link href="/blog/fpv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FPV Racing Quadcopters" /><published>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/blog/fpv</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/fpv/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-this-theme&quot;&gt;How to Use This Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go ahead and read up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;how to install Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too hard I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download this repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iwiedenm/jekyll-theme-massively&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it to any folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a terminal window or a command line and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then enter: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;. You can now access your new Jekyll site from &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000/&lt;/a&gt;. Have fun exploring your new site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;formspree-integration&quot;&gt;Formspree integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contact form below each page on the footer actually collects information! Just change your email address in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">My project is super awesome and special, hire me!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pic02.jpg" /></entry></feed>
